<page>
    <title>Roman Xukhèvitx</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1192784</id>
    <revision>
      <id>13927872</id>
      <parentid>13913762</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-09T11:56:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ArnauBot</username>
        <id>90823</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Robot posa data a plantilles de manteniment</comment>
      <text>{{inacabat|MALLUS|data=agost de 2014}}
{{Fitxa de militar
| nombre =Roman Iòssipovitx Xukhèvitxbr/Роман Йосипович Шухевич
| fechanac = [[30 de juny]] de [[1907]] 
| fechamuerte = [[5 de març]] de [[1950]]
| imagen = Román Shujévych.jpg
| titulo= Roman Xukhèvitx. 1930
| lealtad = {{UKR}}
| rango =[[General]]
| mandos =[[Exèrcit insurgent ucraïnès]]
| lugarnac =[[Krakovets]], [[Galítsia]], [[Imperi austrohongarès]]
| lugarmuerte =[[Lviv]], [[República Socialista Soviètica d'Ucraïna|RSSU]] 
| años de servicio =[[1928]] – [[1950]]
| batallas = [[Segona Guerra Mundial]], guerra per la independència d'Ucraïna.
| condecoraciones =[[Heroi d'Ucraïna]]br /[[File:UPA-strichka.png|30px]] Creu al mèrit militar
}}
'''Roman-Taràs Iòssipovitx Xukhèvitx''' ({{lang-uk|Рома́н-Тарас Йо́сипович Шухе́вич}}, també conegut amb el [[pseudònim]] de '''Taràs Txuprinka''' ({{lang-uk|Тарас Чупринка}} - 30 de juny de 1907 - 5 de març de 1950) va ser un polític [[Ucraïna|ucraïnès]], líder militar i general de l'[[Exèrcit insurgent ucraïnès]] (UPA).

== Biografia == 

=== Infància === 
Romà Tares Yosypovych Shukhevych va néixer a la ciutat de [[Krakovets | Krakovets, Jaworow powiat]], al [[Regne de Galícia i Lodomeria]] situat entre [[Lviv]] i la frontera entre Ucraïna i Polònia d'avui, a [[Ucraïnès persones | Ucraïnès]] - [[poble jueu | jueva]] de la família (pare jueu i mare ucraïnesa) {{citació necessària|data= octubre 2010|data=juliol de 2014}} Tots dos pares de Shukhevych tenien a veure amb el renaixement nacional d'Ucraïna al segle 19 .. La família reclama a dotzenes d'activistes comunitaris actius en la política, la música, la ciència i l'art. Shukhevych rebre la seva educació primerenca fora de Lviv. Va tornar a Lviv per estudiar al gimnàs, que viu amb el seu avi, 01:00 etnògraf. La seva formació política va ser influenciat per [[Yevhen Konovaletz]], el comandant de la [[Organització Militar Ucraïnès]], que va llogar una habitació a la casa del pare de Yevhen Konovaletz 1921-1922.refШах С. Роман Шухевичnbsp;— символ незламності. (Спомин) // Збірник на пошану ген. Романа Шухевича.nbsp;— Мюнхенnbsp;— Лондон: Українська Видавнича Спілка, Український Інститут Освітньої Політики, 1990.nbsp;— С. 149nbsp;— 151. (Shakh. S. Romà Shukhevych - ... Un símbol ininterrompuda (Memòries) // Col·lecció d'articles en honor al general romà Shukhevych Munic, Londres, els editors d'Ucraïna Unió, Institut Ucraïnès d'Educació Política, 1990 p 149) /ref 

=== Joventut === 
A l'octubre de 1926, va entrar al Shukhevych je [[Lviv Institut Politècnic]] per estudiar enginyeria civil.ref[[ДАЛО]].nbsp;— Ф. 27 (Львівська політехніка).nbsp;— Оп. 5.nbsp;— Спр. 18001 (Особова справа студента Львівської політехніки Романа Шухевича).nbsp;— Арк. 4. (SALO) Lviv Politechnic sheet 4./ref In July 1934 he completed his studies with an engineering degree. At this time he was known for his athletic abilities for which he won numerous awards.refГривул Т., Мороз В., Муравський В., Окаринський В. Матеріали до пластового мартиролога.nbsp;— Львів, 2003.nbsp;— С. 113. (Hryvul T., Moroz V, Muravsky V. Okarynsky V. materials regarding the matyrology of PLAST - Lviv 2003 p. 113/ref Ell era també un consumat músic i amb el seu germà Yuriy va realitzar estudis de piano i cant a l'Institut de Música de Lysenko. Va cantar com a solista en ocasions amb el seu germà a la [[Lviv Teatre d'Òpera i Ballet | Lviv opera]]. 

=== Scouting === 
Durant els seus anys d'estudiant al gimnàs, Shukhevych es va convertir en un membre actiu de la [[Scouting]] organització ucraïnesa [[Plast]]. Va ser membre de la [[Lisovi Chorty]]. Va organitzar grups Plast i va fundar la Kurin Chornomortsi (mar Negre cosacs) el 1927.refКравців Б. Людина і вояк // Збірник на пошану ген. Романа Шухевича.nbsp;— Мюнхенnbsp;— Лондон: Українська Видавнича Спілка, Український Інститут Освітньої Політики, 1990.nbsp;— С. 93nbsp;— 95.(Kravtsiv B. Persona i guerrer - .. Col·lecció en honor romà Shukhevych Munic-Londres, Editors d'Ucraïna sindicat, Institut Ucraïnès d'Educació Política, 1990, p 93 /ref 

=== Entrenament militar === 
Des 1928-1929, Shukhevych fer el seu servei militar en l'exèrcit polonès. Com a estudiant d'educació terciària, va ser enviat de forma automàtica per a la formació d'oficials. No obstant això, es va considerar poc fiable, i en el seu lloc va acabar el seu servei militar com a soldat d'artilleria a [[Volhynia]].

=== Organització militar ucraïnesa ===
[[File:Roman Shukhevych.jpg|thumb|150px|Shukhevych in 1930]]
In 1925, Shukhevych joined the [[Ukrainian Military Organization]] (UVO). In 1926, Shukhevych was ordered to assassinate the [[Lviv]] school superintendent, [[Stanisław Sobiński]], accused of Polonizing the Ukrainian education system. The assassination was carried out by Roman Shukhevych and Bohdan Pidhainy on October 19, 1926.ref{{pl icon}} G. Motyka, ''Ukraińska partyzantka, 1942-1960'', PAN, 2006, p. 43/ref In February 1929, the [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]] was founded in [[Vienna]]. Shukhevych under the name Dzvin (Bell) became a representative of the Ukrainian Executive.

Shukhevych was a leader of a wave of attacks against Polish property and homes in Galicia in 1930ref name=SnyderTimothy Snyder, ''Sketches from a Secret War: A Polish Artist's Mission to Liberate Soviet Ukraine'', Yale University Press, 2007, p. 75 [http://books.google.pl/books?id=PKrjew-H0JMCpg=PA75dq=snyder+sabotage+properties+homes]/ref intended to provoke Polish authorities into retaliation refR. J. Crampton,'' Eastern Europe in the twentieth century'',  Routledge, 1994, p. 50 [http://books.google.com/books?id=7Ro-AAAAIAAJpg=PA50lpg=PA50dq=Organization+Ukrainian+Nationalists+sabotage+action+1930source=blots=U0KohAOYMHsig=5nkSGDBRtAgpQrFjTz45T7WXgEUhl=enei=LFN4SuevK4HosQP6kY3lBAsa=Xoi=book_resultct=resultresnum=10]/ref and radicalise Ukrainian society.ref name=Snyder/ The Polish administration retaliated with a process of [[Pacification of Ukrainians in Eastern Galicia (1930)|pacification]] which intensified anti-Polish sentiment and increased [[Ukrainian nationalism]]. {{citació necessària|data= febrer 2011|data=juliol de 2014}}

Shukhevych planned and also participated in terrorist activities and assassinations (sometimes claimed by Ukrainian nationalists to be acts of protest against anti-Ukrainian policies). These included
* the co-ordination of a series of expropriations from Polish government offices in order to fund continued insurrection in the struggle for Ukrainian national determination, i.e. bank robberies and assaults on postal offices or wagons.ref name=G. Motyka, 2006, p. 58{{pl icon}} G. Motyka,'' Ukraińska partyzantka, 1942-1960'', PAN, 2006, p. 58/ref
* the September 1, 1931, assassination of Tadeusz Hołówko, a moderate Polish politician, who advocated cultural autonomy for Ukrainians. His murder caused a shock and was condemned by both societies.ref name=G. Motyka, 2006, p. 58/
* the assassination on March 22, 1932, of Police Commissioner Czechowski
* The unsuccessful attempted assassination of the Soviet consul in Lviv as a protest for the [[Holodomor]] in Central Ukraine by [[Mykola Lemyk]], who mistakenlyref{{pl icon}} G. Motyka, ''Ukraińska partyzantka 1942-1960'', PAN, 2006, p. 60/ref assassinated the special emissary of the NKVD, Alexiy Mayov. {{citació necessària|data= octubre 2009|data=juliol de 2014}}
* the assassination of the Polish minister of internal affairs [[Bronisław Pieracki]], who was declared  by the OUN to be the main person responsible for organizing and executing the 'pacification' and labeled the hangman of the Ukrainian nation.refGabor Lagzi, ''The Ukrainian Radical National Movement in InterWar Poland -the Case of Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists (OUN)'', Regio - Minorities, Politics, Society - English Edition, January 2004/ref The assassination was carried out June 15, 1934, in Warsaw by [[Hryts Matseiko]].refМірчук П. Нарис історії ОУН…nbsp;— С. pp. 337nbsp;— 348, 382nbsp;— 384. (Mirchuk P. Essays in the history of the OUN - pp. 337- 348, 382-384/ref
* the November 30, 1932, assault on the post office in Gródek Jagielloński,ref[[Grzegorz Motyka]], Ukraińska Partyzantka 1942-1960, PAN, 2006, p. 59/ref with Shukhevych's direct participation, in which a number of civilians were killed. {{citació necessària|data= octubre 2009|data=juliol de 2014}}

Shukhevych, [[Stepan Bandera]], [[Stepan Lenkavsky]], [[Yaroslav Stetsko]], [[Yaroslav Starukh]], and others developed the concept of permanent revolution. According to their thesis, the Ukrainian people, being exploited by an occupier, could only obtain freedom through continued pressure on the enemy. As a result, the [[OUN]] took on the responsibility of preparing for an All-Ukrainian revolt. Shukhevych propagated the ideas that the revolution was an uncompromising conflict in order to permanently defeat the foe. {{citació necessària|data= octubre 2010|data=juliol de 2014}}

Shukhevych took an active part in developing a concept regarding the formation of a Ukrainian army. At that time two diametrically opposed arguments existed. The first was to form a Ukrainian army of Ukrainian emigrants, the second a national army to be formed in Western Ukraine organized by Ukrainians.refДАЛО.nbsp;— Ф. 121 (Львівське воєводське управління поліції).nbsp;— Оп. 3.nbsp;— Спр. 1020 (Відомості про діяльність українських націоналістичних організацій УВО і ОУН).nbsp;— Комунікат №nbsp;6: Діяльність Української Військової Організації (УВО), сучасної Організації Українських Націоналістів (ОУН).nbsp;— Арк. 17; Мірчук П. Нарис історії ОУН…nbsp;— С. 138nbsp;— pp. 139, 296nbsp;— 297. (SALO) Fund 121 (Lviv voyevoda direction of Police) Opus 3. Matter 1020 (Materials about the activities of Ukrainian Nationalist Organizations UVO and OUN) - Communication 6; The activities of the Ukrainian Military Organization (UVO), contemporary Organizations of the Ukrainian Nationalists (OUN) Sheet 17; Mirchuk P., ''Essays in the history of the OUN'', pp. 138-139, 296-297/ref

===Imprisonment===
In July 1934, mass arrests took place after the OUN assassination of Internal Affairs minister, [[Bronisław Pieracki|Pieracki]]. On July 18 Shukhevych was arrested; he was sent to the [[Bereza Kartuska Concentration Camp]].refДАЛО.nbsp;— Ф. 255 (Львівська кримінально-слідча тюрма).nbsp;— Оп. 1.nbsp;— Спр. 1532 (Особова справа арештованого Романа Шухевича).nbsp;— Арк. 1nbsp;— 6; Макар В. Береза Картузька: спомини // Спомини та роздуми. Зібрання творів в 4-х томах / За редакцією М. Кулика, Р. Кулика, П.-Й. Потічного.nbsp;— Торонтоnbsp;— Київ, 2001.nbsp;— Т. 4.nbsp;— С. 26nbsp;— 27, 176. (SALO) - Fund 255 (Matters from the Lviv criminal jail - Opus 1, Matter 1532 (Matter regarding the arrested Roman Shukhevych) Sheet 1; Makar V. Bereza Kartuzka - Memoirs - Memoirs and thoughts. Collected works in 4 volumes / edited by M. Kulyk, R. Kulyk, P. Potichny - Toronto-Kyiv, 2001 - Vol. 4 p. 26-27, p. 176/ref In camp he organized a Ukrainian self-defense group. In December 1935 he was acquitted and released from the camp due to lack of evidence.ref name=tp{{ref-llibre|títol=Genocide and Rescue in Wołyń: Recollections of the Ukrainian Nationalist Ethnic Cleansing Campaign Against the Poles During World War II |editorial=MacFarland |autor=Piotrowski, Tadeusz |any=2000 |pàgines=227 | isbn=0786407735}}/ref

During the Warsaw process against the OUN (November 18, 1935 - January 13, 1936) Shukhevych was called as a witness. Shukhevych stood by his right to speak in Ukrainian for which he was fined 200 zloty. After greeting the court with the call Glory to Ukraine, Shukhevych was once again interned.refКниш З. Варшавський процес ОУН на підложжі польсько-українських відносин тієї доби.nbsp;— Торонто: Срібна сурма, 1986.nbsp;— Т. 1.nbsp;— С. 273, 340nbsp;— 341, 354; Варшавський акт обвинувачення Степана Бандери та товаришів / Упорядник Микола Посівнич.nbsp;— Львів: Медицина світу, 2005.nbsp;— С. 10, 159. (Knysh, Z. The Warsaw process of the OUN and the basis for Polish-Ukrainian connections of that era - Toronto; Silver trumpet, 1986, Vol. 1, p. 273, 340-341, 354: The Warsaw Act of incrimination of Stepan Bandera and his colleagues / edited by Mykola Posivnych - Lviv: Medical World, 2005 p. 10, 159/ref

From January 19, 1935, Shukhevych was confined to the [[Bryhidka jail]] in Lviv.refДАЛО.nbsp;— Ф. 255 (Львівська кримінально-слідча тюрма).nbsp;— Оп. 1.nbsp;— Спр. 1744 (Особова справа арештованого Романа Шухевича).nbsp;— Арк. 1. (SALO) - Fund 255 (Lviv criminal investigative jail) Opus 1, Matter 1744 (Personal matter regarding Roman Shukhevych. Sheet 1)/ref He was incarcerated for his membership in the Regional executive of the OUN. The lawyer in the process was his uncle [[Stepan Shukhevych]]. Shukhevych was sentenced to three years in jail; however, because of the 1935 amnesty he was released from jail after spending half a year in the [[Bereza Kartuska Concentration Camp]] refEncyclopedia of Ukraine, ''http://www.encyclopediaofukraine.com/pages/S/H/ShukhevychRoman.htm''/ref  and two years in prison.refPiotrowski, Tadeusz. ''Genocide and Rescue in Wolyn: Recollections of the Ukrainian Nationalist''. McFarland  Company, 2000. ISBN 0-7864-0773-5/ref

After being released in 1937, Shukhevych set up an advertising cooperative called Fama, which became a front for the activities of the OUN. Soon outlets were set up throughout Galicia and Volyn, and within Poland itself. The workers of the company were members of the OUN, often recently released political prisoners. The company was very successful and had sections working with the press and film, publishing booklets, printing posters, selling mineral water, and compiling address listings. It also opened its own transportation section.refЧайківський Б. «Фама». Рекламна фірма Романа Шухевича / Науковий редактор і упорядник В. Кук, М. Посівнич.nbsp;— Львів: Медицина світу, 2005.nbsp;— С. 39nbsp;— 65. (Chaikivsky B. Fama. The advertising agency of Roman Shukhevych. Edited and collected by V. Kuk, M. Posivnych, Lviv: Medical World, 2005 P. 39-65)/ref

===Carpathian Ukraine===
In November 1938, [[Carpatho-Ukraine]] gained autonomy within the [[Czecho-Slovakia|Czecho-Slovak state]]. Shukhevych organized financial aid for the government of the fledgling republic and sent OUN members to set up the [[Carpathian Sich]].
In December 1938, he illegally crossed the border from Poland into [[Czechoslovakia]], traveling to the Ukrainian city of [[Khust]].ref(Кук В. Роман Шухевич…nbsp;— С. 32nbsp;— 33)./ref There, with the aid of local OUN members and [[Abwehr|German intelligence]],refIvan Kazymyrovych Patryliak, Viis’kova diial’nist’ OUN(b) u 1940-1942 rokakh (Kyiv: NAN Ukraїny, 2004) p 265/ref he set up the general headquarters for the fight against the Czecho-Slovak central government.

Moreover, in January 1939 the OUN decided to throw off the autonomous government, which seemed too pro-Czechoslovak to them. The ''[[coup d'état]]'' attempt occurred on the night of March 13–14, in relation to the proclamation of Slovak independence, managed by Germany. With help of sympathizers among the police, the insurgents led by Shukhevych obtained the weapons of the [[gendarmerie]], but their assaults on [[garrison]]s of the Czechoslovak army failed. Just in the [[Khust]] 11 OUN fighters were killed and 51 captured.refPop, Ivan. ''Dějiny Podkarpatské Rusi v datech.'' Libri, Praha 2005. ISBN 80-7277-237-6/ref However, after the [[Slovak Republic (1939–1945)#Creation|Slovak proclamation of independence]] on March 14 and the [[German occupation of Czechoslovakia|Nazis' seizure of Czech lands]] on March 15, Carpatho-Ukraine was immediately invaded and annexed by [[Hungary]]. Shukhevych took an active part in the short-term armed conflict with Hungarian forces and was almost killed in one of the actions. {{citació necessària|data= febrer 2011|data=juliol de 2014}}

After the occupation of [[Carpathian Ukraine]] by Hungary ended, Shukhevych traveled through Romania and Yugoslavia to Austria, where he consulted with OUN commanders and was given new orders and sent to [[Danzig]] to carry out [[subversive]] activities.refЧайківський Б. «Фама»…nbsp;— С. 75nbsp;— 76; Стахів Є. Крізь тюрми, підпілля й кордони. Повість мого життя.nbsp;— Київ: Рада, 1995.nbsp;— С. 50 (B. Chaikivsky, Fama, pp. 75-76; Ye. Stakhiv, ''Through Prisons, Underground and Borders: The story of My Life'', Kyiv, Rada, 1995, p. 50./ref

== Referències ==
{{Commonscat}}
{{Referències}}
{{Autoritat}}
[[Categoria:Ucraïnesos]]</text>
      <sha1>n15yw2t79xe8arhloeba7vi827oz0jf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>